My work focuses on the connection of
عملي يركز على الإتصال بين
both thinking about our community life
كلا من التفكير حول حياتنا الإجتماعية
being part of the environment
وكونها جزء من البيئة
where architecture grows from the natural
حيث تنمو العمارة من الظروف
local conditions and traditions.
الطبيعية والمحلية والعادات
Today I brought two recent projects
واليوم أحضرت مشروعين من مشاريعي الأخيرة
as an example of this.
كمثال على ذلك.
Both projects are in emerging countries,
كلا المشروعان في البلدان الناشئة
one in Ethiopia and another one in Tunisia.
واحد في إثيوبيا، وواحد آخر في تونس.
And also they have in common
وماهو مشترك لديهم
that the different analyses from different perspectives
هو أن التحليلات المختلفة من وجهات النظر المختلفة
becomes an essential part of the final piece of architecture.
تصبح جزءا أساسيا من العمل النهائي للهندسة المعمارية.
The first example started with an invitation
المثال الأول بدأ مع دعوة
to design a multistory shopping mall
لتصميم مركز للتسوق متعددة الطوابق
in Ethiopia's capital city Addis Ababa.
في العاصمة الإثيوبية أديس أبابا.
And this is the type of building
وهذا هو النوع من البناء
we were shown as an example, to my team and myself,
عرض علينا كمثال أنا وفريقي
of what we had to design.
للذي وجب علينا تصميمه
At first, the first thing I thought was,
وكان أول شيء فكرت في البداية
I want to run away.
الهروب
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
After seeing a few of these buildings --
وبعد رؤية عدد قليل من هذه المباني-
there are many in the city --
وهناك العديد منها في هذه المدينة-
we realized that they have three very big points.
لقد أدركنا أن لديهم ثلاث نقاط كبيرة جداً.
First, these buildings, they are almost empty
أولاً، هذه المباني تقريبا فارغة
because they have very large shops
لأنها تحتوي على محلات تجارية كبيرة جداً
where people cannot afford to buy things.
حيث لا يستطيع الناس شراء الأشياء.
Second, they need tons of energy to perform
ثانيا، أنهم بحاجة إلى كم هائل من الطاقة للعمل
because of the skin treatment with glass
بسبب علاج البشرة مع الزجاج
that creates heat in the inside,
الذي يخلق الحرارة في الداخل
and then you need a lot of cooling.
ومن ثم تحتاج إلى الكثير من التبريد.
In a city where this shouldn't happen
وفي مدينة لا ينبغي لهذا أن يحدث
because they have really mild weather
بسبب طقسهم المعتدل
that ranges from 20 to 25 degrees the whole year.
الذي يتراوح من 20 إلى 25 درجة طوال السنة
And third is that their image has nothing to do
وثالثا, هو أن هذه الصورة لا علاقة لها
with Africa and with Ethiopia.
بأفريقيا وإثيوبيا.
It is a pity in a place that has such rich culture and traditions.
وإن هذا لأمر مؤسف في مكان بهذه الثقافة الغنية والتقاليد.
Also during our first visit to Ethiopia,
أيضا خلال زيارتنا الأولى لإثيوبيا،
I was really captivated by the old merkato
كنت حقاً مفتون بميركاتو القديمة
that is this open-air structure
والتي تتميز بمبنى في الهواء الطلق
where thousands of people, they go and buy things
حيث آلاف الناس يذهبون لشراء الأشياء
every day from small vendors.
كل يوم من الباعه الصغار
And also it has this idea of the public space
وأيضا لديها فكرة من الفضاء العام
that uses the outdoors to create activity.
والتي تستغل في الأماكن المفتوحة لخلق الأنشطة
So I thought, this is what I really want to design,
ولذلك فكرت، بأن هذا هو ما أريد تصميمه حقا
not a shopping mall.
وليس مركزا للتسوق
But the question was how we could do a multistory,
ولكن كان السؤال المطروح: كيف يمكن أن نبني مبنى متعدد الطوابق
contemporary building with these principles.
مبنى معاصراً لهذه المبادئ.
The next challenge was when we looked at the site,
فكان التحدي التالي عندما تفقدنا موقع البناء
that is, in a really growing area of the city,
وهو في منطقة حقاً متنامية في المدينة
where most of these buildings that you see in the image,
حيث معظم هذه المباني التي تراها في الصورة،
they were not there.
لم تكن هناك.
And it's also between two parallel streets
وأيضا بين شارعين متوازيين
that don't have any connection for hundreds of meters.
غير موزودة بأي طريقة اتصال لمئات الأمتار.
So the first thing we did was to create a connection
لذا كان أول شيء فعلناه هو بناء إتصال
between these two streets,
بين الشارعين
putting all the entrances of the building.
بوضع جميع مداخل المبنى.
And this extends with an inclined atrium
وهذا يمتد مع نفق منحدر
that creates an open-air space in the building
يخلق مكانا مفتوحا في المبنى
that self-protects itself with its own shape
ويحمي نفسه ذاتيا بطبيعة شكله
from the sun and the rain.
من الشمس والمطر.
And around this void
وحول هذا المكان الخالي
we placed this idea of the market with small shops,
وضعنا فكرة التسوق من المتاجر الصغيرة
that change in each floor because of the shape of the void.
التي تتغير في كل طابق بسبب شكل المكان
I also thought, how to close the building?
وفكرت أيضا، بكيفية إغلاق المبنى؟
And I really wanted to find a solution
وأردت حقاً أن أجد حلاً
that would respond to the local climate conditions.
مطاوعا للظروف المناخية المحلية.
And I started thinking about the textile
وبدأت في التفكير حول المنسوجات
like a shell made of concrete
مثل قذيفة مصنوعة من الخرسانة
with perforations that would let the air in,
بثقوب تسمح بدخول الهواء
and also the light, but in a filtered way.
والضوء، ولكن بطريقة مصفية
And then the inspiration came from these beautiful patterns of the Ethiopian women's dresses.
ومن ثم جاء الإلهام من هذه الأزرار الجميلة من فساتين المرأة الإثيوبية.
That they have fractal geometry properties
والتي تحتوي على خصائص هندسة كسورية
and this helped me to shape the whole facade.
وهذا ساعدني على تشكيل الواجهة كلها
And we are building that
ونحن بصدد بناءه
with these small prefabricated pieces
مع هذه القطع الجاهزة الصغيرة
that are the windows that let the air and the light
وهي النوافذ التي تسمح بدخول الهواء والضوء
in a controlled way inside the building.
بطريقة متحكم بها داخل المبنى
And this is complemented by these small colored glasses
ويستكمل ذلك بقطع الزجاج الملونة الصغيرة
that use the light from the inside of the building
والتي تستفيد من الضوء من داخل المبنى
to light up the building at night.
لتضيء المبنى في الليل
With these ideas it was not easy first to convince the developers
ومع هذه الأفكار لم يكن من السهل إقناع المطورين في البداية
because they were like,
لأنهم كانوا يقولون:
"This is not a shopping mall. We didn't ask for that."
"هذا ليس مركز للتسوق. ونحن لم يطلب ذلك. "
But then we all realized that this idea of the market
ولكن بعدها أدركنا جميعا أن هذه الفكرة من السوق المفتوحة
happened to be a lot more profitable than the idea of the shopping mall
مربحة أكثر بكثير من فكرة السوق المغلقة
because basically they had more shops to sell.
لأنه كان لديهم أساسا محلات بيع أكثر
And also that the idea of the facade was much, much cheaper,
وكما أن فكرة واجهة المبنى كانت أرخص بكثير،
not only because of the material compared with the glass,
ليس فقط بسبب المواد مقارنة بالزجاج
but also because we didn't need to have air conditioning anymore.
ولكن أيضا لأننا لم نكن بحاجة إلى أجهزة التكييف بعد الآن.
So we created some budget savings
لذا قمنا بوضع ميزانية من المدخرات
that we used to implement the project.
وصرفناها لتنفيذ المشروع.
And the first implementation was to think
وكان أول تنفيذ هو التفكير
about how we could make the building self-sufficient in terms of energy
حول كيفية جعل المبنى مكتفية ذاتيا من حيث الطاقة
in a city that has electricity cuts almost every day.
في مدينة ينقطع فيها الكهرباء كل يوم تقريبا
So we created a huge asset by placing photovoltaics there on the roof.
لذا أنشأنا ثروة ضخمة بوضع وحدات الطاقة الشمسية على السطح هناك
And then under those panels
ومن ثم تحت تلك اللوحات
we thought about the roof like a new public space with gathering areas and bars
كنا نرى السقف مثل المكان الجديد للشعب مزودا بأماكن للتجمع
that would create this urban oasis.
من شأنها أن تخلق واحة حضارية
And these porches on the roof,
وهذه الشرفات في السقف
all together they collect the water to reuse for sanitation on the inside.
تجمع معا الماء لإعادة إستعماله للصرف الصحي في الداخل
Hopefully by the beginning of next year, because we are already on the fifth floor of the construction.
ونأمل حدوث ذلك مع بداية العام المقبل، نظراً لأننا حاليا نعمل في الطابق الخامس للبناء.
The second example is a master plan
والمثال الثاني هو عبارة عن خطة رئيسية
of 2,000 apartments and facilities in the city of Tunis.
لـ 2000 شقة وتسهيلات في مدينة تونس
And for doing such a big project, the biggest project I've ever designed,
و للقيام بمثل هذا المشروع الكبير والذي يعتبر أكبر المشاريع التي قمت بتصميمها
I really needed to understand the city of Tunis,
فقد كنت بحاجة إلى فهم بمدينة تونس
but also its surroundings and the tradition and culture.
وكذلك المناطق المحيطة بها والتقاليد والثقافة
During that analysis I paid special attention to the medina
وخلال هذا التحليل، أوليت اهتماما خاصا للمدينة المنورة
that is this 1,000-year-old structure that used to be closed by a wall,
وهو هذا الهيكل الذي يبلغ 1,000 عاماً وأغلق بواسطة جدار
opened by twelve different gates, connected by almost straight lines.
مفتوحا بواسطة اثني عشر بوابات مختلفة، متصلة بخطوط مستقيمة تقريبا.
When I went to the site, the first design operation we did
وعندما ذهبت إلى الموقع، أول عملية قمنا بها لتصميم
was to extend the existing streets, creating 12 initial blocks
كانت لتوسيع الشوارع القائمة، وإنشاء 12 مباني أولية
similar in size and characteristics to the ones we have in Barcelona
مماثلة في الحجم والخصائص لتلك التي لدينا في برشلونة
and other cities in Europe with these courtyards.
والمدن الأخرى في أوروبا مع هذه الساحات
On top of that, we selected some strategic points
علاوة على ذلك، حددنا بعض النقاط الاستراتيجية
reminded of this idea of the gates and connecting them by straight lines,
بناءً على هذه الفكرة من البوابات وربطها بخطوط مستقيمة
and this modified this initial pattern.
وهذا عدل هذا النمط الأولى.
And the last operation was to think about the cell,
وكانت آخر عملية هي التفكير في الأجزاء الصغير
the small cell of the project, like the apartment,
أصغر جزء في المشروع، مثل الشقة
as an essential part of the master plan.
كجزء أساسي من الخطة الرئيسية
And for that I thought, what would be the best orientation
و لذلك فكرت، ما هو الاتجاه الأفضل
in the Mediterranean climate for an apartment?
في مناخ البحر الأبيض المتوسط للشقة؟
And it's north-south, because it creates a thermal difference between both sides of the house
ومن الشمال والجنوب، لأنه يخلق فرقا حرارية بين كلا الجانبين من المنزل
and then a natural ventilation.
وبعد ذلك تهوية طبيعية
So we overlap a pattern that makes sure that most of the apartments
لذا قمنا بعمل تداخل لنمط يؤكد لنا من أن معظم الشقق
are perfectly oriented in that direction.
هي موجهة بعناية نحو الإتجاه المقصود
And this is the result
وهذه هي النتيجة
that is almost like a combination of the European block and the Arab city.
كانت تقريبا تجمع بين بين المباني الأوروبية والمدينة العربية.
It has these blocks with courtyards,
لديها هذه المباني في الساحات
and then on the ground floor
ومن ثم في الطابق الأرضي
you have all these connections for the pedestrians.
لديك جميع الاتصالات للمارة.
And also it responds to the local regulations that establish
وأيضا فإنه يستجيب للأنظمة المحلية الموضوعة
a higher density on the upper levels and a lower density on the ground floor.
بكثافة أعلى في الطوابق العليا، وكثاقة أقل في الطابق الأرضي.
And it also reinforces this idea of the gates.
وأنه أيضا يعزز هذه الفكرة من البوابات.
The volume has this connecting shape
ويتميز الحجم بهذا الشكل المربوط
that shades itself with three different types of apartments
الذي يظل نفسه مع ثلاثة أنواع مختلفة من الشقق
and also lets the light go on the ground floor in a very dense neighborhood
ويتيح أيضا للضوء للدخول في الطابق الأرضي في حي كثيف جداً
And in the courtyards there are the different facilities,
وفي الساحات يوجد مرافق مختلفة
such as a gym and a kindergarten
مثل الصالة الرياضية وروضة للأطفال
and close by, a series of commercial [spaces] that bring activity to the ground floor.
ومغلقة بـسلسلة تجارية من المحلات الصغيرة التي تجلب النشاط إلى الطابق الأرضي.
The roof, which is my favorite space of the project
والسقف، وهو أفضل مكان لي في للمشروع
is almost like giving back to the community the space taken by the construction.
يعتبر بمثابة المكان المسترد للحي الذي أخذ بفعل المبنى
And it's where all the neighbors, they can go up and socialize,
وهو المكان الذي يمكن أن يتعرف الجيران على بعض
and do activities such as having a two-kilometer run in the morning,
وأن يقوموا بأنشطة مثل الركض لمسافة كيلومترين في الصباح
jumping from one building to another.
والقفز من مبنى إلى آخر
These two examples,
هذان المثالان،
they have a common approach in the design process.
لديهم نهج مشترك في عملية التصميم.
And also, they are in emerging countries where you can see
وأيضا، يقعان فيي البلدان النامية، كما هو واضح
the cities literally growing.
فالمدن في حالة نمو حرفيا
In these cities, the impact of architecture in people's lives of today and tomorrow
وفي هذه المدن، تأثير الهندسة المعمارية في حياة الناس اليوم والغد
changes the local communities and economies at the same speed as the buildings grow.
تغير في المجتمعات والاقتصادات المحلية بنفس السرعة كما تنمو المباني
For this reason, I see even more importance
لهذا السبب، فإنني أرى أهمية أكثر
to look at architecture finding simple but affordable solutions
لإلقاء النظرة على العمارة والهنذسة وإيجاد حلول بسيطة ولكن بأسعار معقولة
that enhance the relationship between the community and the environment
حلول يمكن أن تعزز العلاقة بين المجتمع والبيئة
and that aim to connect nature and people.
والتي تهدف إلى ربط الطبيعة والناس.
Thank you very much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)